<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on OSAIL</title>
    <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/projects/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on OSAIL</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Image Annotation</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/projects/image-annotation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/projects/image-annotation/</guid>
      <description>Manual annotation of medical images is time-consuming, error-prone, and subject to inter-reader variability. OSAIL develops cutting-edge deep learning algorithms that automate these tasks, allowing for accelerated creation of labeled datasets and algorithms that benefit from an abundance of data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Image Registries</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/projects/image-registries/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/projects/image-registries/</guid>
      <description>A common lament in data science is that most of a researcher&amp;rsquo;s time is spent organizing and cleaning data for further analysis. OSAIL has invested heavily in the creation of large-scale imaging registries with images pulled from Mayo Clinic&amp;rsquo;s electronic health record system and automatically labeled for future use with bespoke annotation algorithms. These registries allow for rapid project progression and large cohort studies which would be otherwise prohibitively laborious.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Risk Stratification</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/projects/risk-stratification/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/projects/risk-stratification/</guid>
      <description>Joint replacement surgeries are some of the most commonly performed procedures in the world. While joint failure following these procedures is rare, it does happen, and it can be catastrophic for the patient. OSAIL is a leading advocate of personalized medicine in orthopedics, where characteristics of the individual patients are used as inputs to models that predict risk of post-operative complications. These models have the potential to help surgeons optimize their approach for maximally beneficial post-operative outcomes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Synthetic Data</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/projects/synthetic-data-generation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/projects/synthetic-data-generation/</guid>
      <description>Image generation is the umbrella term for deep learning projects that aim to generate synthetic imaging data resembling real imaging. Synthetic images protect patient privacy and also allow for substantially larger data sets for algorithm development. To date, OSAIL has created algorithms that generate synthetic imaging datasets, improve the quality of existing images through resolution upscaling or artifact reduction, and modify real images with synthetic pixels.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Text Processing</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/projects/text-processing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/projects/text-processing/</guid>
      <description>OSAIL develops NLP models that are able to parse and synthesize text data, from operative notes to progress notes and lab values. These models have a variety of uses, from distilling unstrctured data for use in conjunction with our imaging registries, to predicting surgical outcomes from automatically pulled patient characteristics.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
