<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>OSAIL</title>
    <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on OSAIL</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>New Website!</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/news/09-15-2022_news/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/news/09-15-2022_news/</guid>
      <description>Say hello to the new OSAIL website! We will use this platform to share publications, upcoming presentations, and interactive demos developed by the lab.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>All You Need is 20 Images: Few-shot Image Segmentation Using Denoising Diffusion Probabilistic Models</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_cmimi_ddpm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_cmimi_ddpm/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Applying Deep Learning to Establish a Total Hip Arthroplasty Radiography Registry: A Stepwise Approach</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_cmimi_styleganimggen/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_cmimi_styleganimggen/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Applying Deep Learning to Establish a Total Hip Arthroplasty Radiography Registry: A Stepwise Approach</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_cmimi_tharegistry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_cmimi_tharegistry/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Applying Deep Learning to Establish a Total Hip Arthroplasty Radiography Registry: A Stepwise Approach</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_siim_tharegistry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_siim_tharegistry/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting risk of dislocation after total hip arthroplasty from preoperative radiographs: A multitask multimodal deep learning approach</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_siim_thadiscalc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_siim_thadiscalc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Denoising Diffusion Probabilistic Models to Create High Resolution Synthetic Pelvis Radiographs</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_cmimi_supersizedimg/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_cmimi_supersizedimg/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Applying Deep Learning to Establish a Total Hip Arhroplasty Radiography Registry: A Stepwise Approach</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_jbjs_tharegistry/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_jbjs_tharegistry/</guid>
      <description>Background: Establishing imaging registries for large patient cohorts is challenging because manual labeling is tedious and relying solely on DICOM (digital imaging and communications in medicine) metadata can result in errors. We endeavored to establish an automated hip and pelvic radiography registry of total hip arthroplasty (THA) patients by utilizing deep-learning pipelines. The aims of the study were (1) to utilize these automated pipelines to identify all pelvic and hip radiographs with appropriate annotation of laterality and presence or absence of implants, and (2) to automatically measure acetabular component inclination and version for THA images.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multicenter Validation of Natural Language Processing Algorithms for the Detection of Common Data Elements in Operative Notes for Total Hip Arthroplasty: Algorithm Development and Validation</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_jmir_nlp_validationthaopnote/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_jmir_nlp_validationthaopnote/</guid>
      <description>Background: Natural language processing (NLP) methods are powerful tools for extracting and analyzing critical information from free-text data. MedTaggerIE, an open-source NLP pipeline for information extraction based on text patterns, has been widely used in the annotation of clinical notes. A rule-based system, MedTagger-total hip arthroplasty (THA), developed based on MedTaggerIE, was previously shown to correctly identify the surgical approach, fixation, and bearing surface from the THA operative notes at Mayo Clinic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distribution and Correlates of Hip-Knee-Ankle Angle in Early Osteoarthritis and Preoperative Total Knee Arthroplasty Patients</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_joa_mip_hipkneeankleangle/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_joa_mip_hipkneeankleangle/</guid>
      <description>Background: Several studies have investigated the distribution of hip-knee-ankle (HKA) angle in healthy populations; however, few have evaluated this metric in patients undergoing total knee arthroplasty (TKA). The purpose of this study is to compare HKA angle distribution in early and advanced knee osteoarthritis (OA) patients.
Methods: Full limb radiographs were used to measure HKA angle for 983 subjects from the Osteoarthritis Initiative (OAI) cohort and 4,901 pre-TKA patients from an institutional cohort.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying Modifiable and Nonmodifiable Cost Drivers of Ambulatory Rotator Cuff Repair: A Machine Learning Analysis</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_jses_ml_costrcr/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_jses_ml_costrcr/</guid>
      <description>Introduction: Implementing novel tools that identify contributors to the cost of orthopedic procedures can help hospitals maximize efficiency, minimize waste, improve surgical decision-making, and practice value-based care. The purpose of this study was to develop and internally validate a machine learning algorithm to identify key drivers of total charges after ambulatory arthroscopic rotator cuff repair and compare its performance with a state-of-the-art statistical learning model.
Methods: A retrospective review of the New York State Ambulatory Surgery and Services Database was performed to identify patients who underwent elective outpatient rotator cuff repair (RCR) from 2015 to 2016.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning for Radiographic Measurement of Femoral Componenent Subsidence Following Total Hip Arthroplasty</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_radai_mip_thasubsidence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_radai_mip_thasubsidence/</guid>
      <description>Femoral component subsidence following total hip arthroplasty (THA) is a worrisome radiographic finding. This study developed and evaluated a deep learning tool to automatically quantify femoral component subsidence between two serial anteroposterior (AP) hip radiographs. The authors&amp;rsquo; institutional arthroplasty registry was used to retrospectively identify patients who underwent primary THA from 2000 to 2020. A deep learning dynamic U-Net model was trained to automatically segment femur, implant, and magnification markers on a dataset of 500 randomly selected AP hip radiographs from 386 patients with polished tapered cemented femoral stems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Redefining the 3D Topography of the Acetabular Safe Zone: A Multivariable Study Evaluating Prosthetic Hip Stability</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_aaos_acetabularsafezone/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_aaos_acetabularsafezone/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creation of a Total Hip Arthroplasty Patient Specific Dislocation Risk Calculator Augmented by Deep Learning Radiograph Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_aaos_thadislocation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_aaos_thadislocation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning Tool for Accurate and Precise Automatic Measurement of Femoral Component Subsidence Following Total Hip Arthroplasty from Plan Radiographs</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_aaos_thasubsidence/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_aaos_thasubsidence/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Redefining the 3D Topography of the Acetabular Safe Zone: A Multivariable Study Evaluating Prosthetic Hip Stability</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_jbjs_mip_acetabularsafezone/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_jbjs_mip_acetabularsafezone/</guid>
      <description>Background: Dislocation is the most common reason for early revision following total hip arthroplasty (THA). More than 40 years ago, Lewinnek et al. proposed an acetabular &amp;ldquo;safe zone&amp;rdquo; to avoid dislocation. While novel at the time, their study was substantially limited according to modern standards. The purpose of this study was to determine optimal acetabular cup positioning during THA as well as the effect of surgical approach on the topography of the acetabular safe zone and the hazard of dislocation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning Tool for Accurate and Precise Automatic Measurement of Femoral Component Subsidence Following THA</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_aahks_thasubsidence/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_aahks_thasubsidence/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning Artificial Intelligence Model for Prediction of Hip Dislocation Following Primary Total Hip Arthroplasty From Anteroposterior Radiographs</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_aaos_thadisrisk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_aaos_thadisrisk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Deep Learning Tool for Automated Radiographic Measurement of Acetabular Component Inclination and Version After Total Hip Arthroplasty</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_joa_mip_thaacetabularangles/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_joa_mip_thaacetabularangles/</guid>
      <description>Background: Inappropriate acetabular component angular position is believed to increase the risk of hip dislocation after total hip arthroplasty. However, manual measurement of these angles is time consuming and prone to interobserver variability. The purpose of this study was to develop a deep learning tool to automate the measurement of acetabular component angles on postoperative radiographs.
Methods: Two cohorts of 600 anteroposterior (AP) pelvis and 600 cross-table lateral hip postoperative radiographs were used to develop deep learning models to segment the acetabular component and the ischial tuberosities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning Artificial Intelligence Model for Assessment of Hip Dislocation Risk Following Primary Total hip Arthroplasty from Postoperative Radiographs</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_joa_riskpred_thadislocation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_joa_riskpred_thadislocation/</guid>
      <description>Background: Dislocation is a common complication following total hip arthroplasty (THA), and accounts for a high percentage of subsequent revisions. The purpose of this study is to illustrate the potential of a convolutional neural network model to assess the risk of hip dislocation based on postoperative anteroposterior pelvis radiographs.
Methods: We retrospectively evaluated radiographs for a cohort of 13,970 primary THAs with 374 dislocations over 5 years of follow-up. Overall, 1490 radiographs from dislocated and 91,094 from non-dislocated THAs were included in the analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning Tool for Accurate and Precise Automatic Measurement of Femoral Component Subsidence Following Total Hip Arthroplasty from Plan Radiographs</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_mayoai_thasubsidence/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_mayoai_thasubsidence/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use of Natural Language Processing Algorithms to Identify Common Data Elements in Operative Notes for Knee Arthroplasty</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_joa_nlp_tkaopnote/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_joa_nlp_tkaopnote/</guid>
      <description>Background: Natural language processing (NLP) methods have the capability to process clinical free text in electronic health records, decreasing the need for costly manual chart review, and improving data quality. We developed rule-based NLP algorithms to automatically extract surgery specific data elements from knee arthroplasty operative notes.
Methods: Within a cohort of 20,000 knee arthroplasty operative notes from 2000 to 2017 at a large tertiary institution, we randomly selected independent pairs of training and test sets to develop and evaluate NLP algorithms to detect five major data elements.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Autommated Detection of Periprosthetic Joint Infections and Data Elements Using Natural Language Processing</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_joa_nlp_pji/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_joa_nlp_pji/</guid>
      <description>Background: Periprosthetic joint infection (PJI) data elements are contained in both structured and unstructured documents in electronic health records and require manual data collection. The goal of this study is to develop a natural language processing (NLP) algorithm to replicate manual chart review for PJI data elements.
Methods: PJI was identified among all total joint arthroplasty (TJA) procedures performed at a single academic institution between 2000 and 2017. Data elements that comprise the Musculoskeletal Infection Society (MSIS) criteria were manually extracted and used as the gold standard for validation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning Artificial Intelligence Model for Assessment of Hip Dislocation Risk Following Primary Total Hip Arthroplasty From Postoperative Radiographs</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/20_rsna_thadisrisk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/20_rsna_thadisrisk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning Artificial Intelligence Model for Measurement of the Acetabular Inclination and Anteversion Angles Following Total Hip Arthroplasty</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/20_cmimi_thaacetabularangles/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/20_cmimi_thaacetabularangles/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning Artificial Intelligence Model for Prediction of Hip Dislocation Following Primary Total Hip Arthroplasty From Postoperative Radiographs</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/20_cmimi_thadisrisk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/20_cmimi_thadisrisk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use of Natural Language Processing Algorithms to Identify Common Data Elements in Operative Notes for Total Hip Arthroplasty</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/19_jbjs_nlp_thaopnote/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/19_jbjs_nlp_thaopnote/</guid>
      <description>Background: Manual chart review is labor-intensive and requires specialized knowledge possessed by highly trained medical professionals. Natural language processing (NLP) tools are distinctive in their ability to extract critical information from raw text in electronic health records (EHRs). As a proof of concept for the potential application of this technology, we examined the ability of NLP to correctly identify common elements described by surgeons in operative notes for total hip arthroplasty (THA).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use of Natural Language Processing Tools to Identify and Classify Periprosthetic Femur Fractures</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/19_joa_nlp_ppfx/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/19_joa_nlp_ppfx/</guid>
      <description>Background: Manual chart review is labor-intensive and requires specialized knowledge possessed by highly trained medical professionals. The cost and infrastructure challenges required to implement this is prohibitive for most hospitals. Natural language processing (NLP) tools are distinctive in their ability to extract critical information from unstructured text in the electronic health records. As a simple proof-of-concept for the potential application of NLP technology in total hip arthroplasty (THA), we examined its ability to identify periprosthetic femur fractures (PPFFx) followed by more complex Vancouver classification.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/contact/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/contact/contact/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/people/bardia_k/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/people/bardia_k/</guid>
      <description>Bardia Khosravi is a MD, with two masters in medical education (MHPE) and public health (MPH), from Tehran University of Medical Sciences (TUMS). He has been a full stack developer since he was 19. Since the pandemic, he started focusing his programming skills on deep learning as way of helping those suffering with the disease, through early diagnosis and efficient triage. He started his research at RIL in 2021 and has been working on complications&amp;rsquo; risk prediction in orthopedic patients, and other generative tasks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/people/christina_s/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/people/christina_s/</guid>
      <description>Christina has an educational background in Healthcare Administration with a focus in management. She has worked at Mayo Clinic for 12 years with 9 years focused in research program management across Hematology, Epidemiology and most recently Orthopedic Surgery. Christina serves as Lab Manager of OSAIL, supporting the lab directors and the infrastructure of the lab and its crucial collaborations across.
OSAIL@mayo.edu</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/people/cody_w/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/people/cody_w/</guid>
      <description>Dr. Wyles holds dual appointments as an Assistant Professor of Orthopedic Surgery and Clinical Anatomy and has a surgical practice focused on complex hip and knee reconstruction at Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota. He has authored 150 peer-reviewed publications, 4 Hip Society and Knee Society Awards, CORR® ORS Richard A. Brand Award for Outstanding Orthopaedic Research, and several other notable awards in orthopedic research. His primary research interest is leveraging the tools of AI to enhance patient-specific phenotyping and assess the natural history of degenerative hip and knee diseases for improved predictive analytics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/people/joaquin_s/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/people/joaquin_s/</guid>
      <description>Dr. Sanchez-Sotelo practices as Consultant in the Department of Orthopedic Surgery at Mayo Clinic. He is also appointed as Professor at Mayo College of Medicine. He serves as Division Chair of Shoulder and Elbow Surgery, and Chairman of the Orthopedic Research Review Committee at Mayo Clinic, and Liaison for the Department of Orthopedic Surgery with Mayo Clinic Media Relationships. He has been presented the Mayo Clinic Teacher of the Year Award on two separate occasions and has received other awards in the past, including the Mark B.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/people/john_m/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/people/john_m/</guid>
      <description>John Mickley is a medical student from The Ohio State University and currently works as a research fellow at Mayo Clinic Orthopedic Surgery Artificial Intelligence Laboratory (OSAIL). He is new to the artificial intelligence field, but loves learning and participating in cutting-edge work with the OSAIL team. John participates in a variety tasks throughout the research process from idea creation, annotation, and data cleaning, to statistical analysis, figure creation, and manuscript preparation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/people/kellen_m/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/people/kellen_m/</guid>
      <description>Kellen received his B.A. from St. Olaf College in 2017 and his Ph.D. from the University of Minnesota in 2022 doing ultra-high field MRI research with a healthy smattering of AI. He was the recipient of an NCATS TL1 fellowship from 2020-2022 and is always thinking of how research translates to the clinic. Kellen is especially attuned to the data engineering side of research problems with huge scale imaging datasets and loves a good ETL pipeline.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/people/linjun_y/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/people/linjun_y/</guid>
      <description>Linjun graduated from University of Iowa with a major in biomedical engineering. He is currently working as a data scientist in the orthopedic surgery artificial intelligence laboratory. The goal of his job is to develop AI solutions for orthopedic surgeons. His daily work includes computer programming, AI algorithm design, data management, and reading literatures. Working in an interdisciplinary team is definitely challenging but interesting and motivating.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/people/michael_t/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/people/michael_t/</guid>
      <description>Dr. Taunton is a Professor of Orthopedic Surgery at the Mayo Clinic in Rochester MN. He is the program director of the Hip and Knee Reconstruction fellowship at Mayo Clinic. Dr. Taunton is also the Co-director of the Orthopedic Surgery Artificial Intelligence Lab at Mayo Clinic. He is a fellowship trained orthopedic surgeon in hip and knee reconstruction. His special interests are the direct anterior approach for total hip arthroplasty, advanced pelvic and femoral reconstruction for revision total hip arthroplasty, as well as knee arthroplasty, and machine learning algorithms applied to the arthroplasty practice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/people/noelle_l/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/people/noelle_l/</guid>
      <description>A. Noelle Larson, MD, FAAOS, FAOA, is a pediatric orthopedic surgeon at the Mayo Clinic. Her interests include scoliosis, CT-guided navigation, and non-fusion scoliosis surgery. She works to safely innovate and bring new treatments to patients with scoliosis and leverage the power of new technology for improved quality of care. She leads several research studies evaluating posterior dynamic distraction, and other scoliosis surgeries and is principal investigator for an FDA study of vertebral body tethering.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/people/pouria_r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/people/pouria_r/</guid>
      <description>Pouria is a graduated physician from Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Iran, and has also earned a Master of Public Health and a Master of Health Professions Education from the same university. He currently works as a post-doctorate research fellow and data scientist at Mayo Clinic Artificial Intelligence Laboratory and the Orthopedic Surgery Artificial Intelligence Laboratory (OSAIL), Mayo Clinic. His daily job includes programming, data science research, and looking to apply artificial intelligence in medicine and medical imaging.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Image Annotation</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/projects/image-annotation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/projects/image-annotation/</guid>
      <description>Manual annotation of medical images is time-consuming, error-prone, and subject to inter-reader variability. OSAIL develops cutting-edge deep learning algorithms that automate these tasks, allowing for accelerated creation of labeled datasets and algorithms that benefit from an abundance of data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Image Registries</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/projects/image-registries/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/projects/image-registries/</guid>
      <description>A common lament in data science is that most of a researcher&amp;rsquo;s time is spent organizing and cleaning data for further analysis. OSAIL has invested heavily in the creation of large-scale imaging registries with images pulled from Mayo Clinic&amp;rsquo;s electronic health record system and automatically labeled for future use with bespoke annotation algorithms. These registries allow for rapid project progression and large cohort studies which would be otherwise prohibitively laborious.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Risk Stratification</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/projects/risk-stratification/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/projects/risk-stratification/</guid>
      <description>Joint replacement surgeries are some of the most commonly performed procedures in the world. While joint failure following these procedures is rare, it does happen, and it can be catastrophic for the patient. OSAIL is a leading advocate of personalized medicine in orthopedics, where characteristics of the individual patients are used as inputs to models that predict risk of post-operative complications. These models have the potential to help surgeons optimize their approach for maximally beneficial post-operative outcomes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Synthetic Data</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/projects/synthetic-data-generation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/projects/synthetic-data-generation/</guid>
      <description>Image generation is the umbrella term for deep learning projects that aim to generate synthetic imaging data resembling real imaging. Synthetic images protect patient privacy and also allow for substantially larger data sets for algorithm development. To date, OSAIL has created algorithms that generate synthetic imaging datasets, improve the quality of existing images through resolution upscaling or artifact reduction, and modify real images with synthetic pixels.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Text Processing</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/projects/text-processing/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/projects/text-processing/</guid>
      <description>OSAIL develops NLP models that are able to parse and synthesize text data, from operative notes to progress notes and lab values. These models have a variety of uses, from distilling unstrctured data for use in conjunction with our imaging registries, to predicting surgical outcomes from automatically pulled patient characteristics.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
