<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>People on OSAIL</title>
    <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/people/</link>
    <description>Recent content in People on OSAIL</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/people/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/people/bardia_k/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/people/bardia_k/</guid>
      <description>Bardia Khosravi is a MD, with two masters in medical education (MHPE) and public health (MPH), from Tehran University of Medical Sciences (TUMS). He has been a full stack developer since he was 19. Since the pandemic, he started focusing his programming skills on deep learning as way of helping those suffering with the disease, through early diagnosis and efficient triage. He started his research at RIL in 2021 and has been working on complications&amp;rsquo; risk prediction in orthopedic patients, and other generative tasks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/people/christina_s/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/people/christina_s/</guid>
      <description>Christina has an educational background in Healthcare Administration with a focus in management. She has worked at Mayo Clinic for 12 years with 9 years focused in research program management across Hematology, Epidemiology and most recently Orthopedic Surgery. Christina serves as Lab Manager of OSAIL, supporting the lab directors and the infrastructure of the lab and its crucial collaborations across.
OSAIL@mayo.edu</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/people/cody_w/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/people/cody_w/</guid>
      <description>Dr. Wyles holds dual appointments as an Assistant Professor of Orthopedic Surgery and Clinical Anatomy and has a surgical practice focused on complex hip and knee reconstruction at Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota. He has authored 150 peer-reviewed publications, 4 Hip Society and Knee Society Awards, CORR® ORS Richard A. Brand Award for Outstanding Orthopaedic Research, and several other notable awards in orthopedic research. His primary research interest is leveraging the tools of AI to enhance patient-specific phenotyping and assess the natural history of degenerative hip and knee diseases for improved predictive analytics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/people/joaquin_s/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/people/joaquin_s/</guid>
      <description>Dr. Sanchez-Sotelo practices as Consultant in the Department of Orthopedic Surgery at Mayo Clinic. He is also appointed as Professor at Mayo College of Medicine. He serves as Division Chair of Shoulder and Elbow Surgery, and Chairman of the Orthopedic Research Review Committee at Mayo Clinic, and Liaison for the Department of Orthopedic Surgery with Mayo Clinic Media Relationships. He has been presented the Mayo Clinic Teacher of the Year Award on two separate occasions and has received other awards in the past, including the Mark B.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/people/john_m/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/people/john_m/</guid>
      <description>John Mickley is a medical student from The Ohio State University and currently works as a research fellow at Mayo Clinic Orthopedic Surgery Artificial Intelligence Laboratory (OSAIL). He is new to the artificial intelligence field, but loves learning and participating in cutting-edge work with the OSAIL team. John participates in a variety tasks throughout the research process from idea creation, annotation, and data cleaning, to statistical analysis, figure creation, and manuscript preparation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/people/kellen_m/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/people/kellen_m/</guid>
      <description>Kellen received his B.A. from St. Olaf College in 2017 and his Ph.D. from the University of Minnesota in 2022 doing ultra-high field MRI research with a healthy smattering of AI. He was the recipient of an NCATS TL1 fellowship from 2020-2022 and is always thinking of how research translates to the clinic. Kellen is especially attuned to the data engineering side of research problems with huge scale imaging datasets and loves a good ETL pipeline.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/people/linjun_y/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/people/linjun_y/</guid>
      <description>Linjun graduated from University of Iowa with a major in biomedical engineering. He is currently working as a data scientist in the orthopedic surgery artificial intelligence laboratory. The goal of his job is to develop AI solutions for orthopedic surgeons. His daily work includes computer programming, AI algorithm design, data management, and reading literatures. Working in an interdisciplinary team is definitely challenging but interesting and motivating.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/people/michael_t/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/people/michael_t/</guid>
      <description>Dr. Taunton is a Professor of Orthopedic Surgery at the Mayo Clinic in Rochester MN. He is the program director of the Hip and Knee Reconstruction fellowship at Mayo Clinic. Dr. Taunton is also the Co-director of the Orthopedic Surgery Artificial Intelligence Lab at Mayo Clinic. He is a fellowship trained orthopedic surgeon in hip and knee reconstruction. His special interests are the direct anterior approach for total hip arthroplasty, advanced pelvic and femoral reconstruction for revision total hip arthroplasty, as well as knee arthroplasty, and machine learning algorithms applied to the arthroplasty practice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/people/noelle_l/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/people/noelle_l/</guid>
      <description>A. Noelle Larson, MD, FAAOS, FAOA, is a pediatric orthopedic surgeon at the Mayo Clinic. Her interests include scoliosis, CT-guided navigation, and non-fusion scoliosis surgery. She works to safely innovate and bring new treatments to patients with scoliosis and leverage the power of new technology for improved quality of care. She leads several research studies evaluating posterior dynamic distraction, and other scoliosis surgeries and is principal investigator for an FDA study of vertebral body tethering.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/people/pouria_r/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/OSAIL.github.io/people/pouria_r/</guid>
      <description>Pouria is a graduated physician from Tehran University of Medical Sciences, Iran, and has also earned a Master of Public Health and a Master of Health Professions Education from the same university. He currently works as a post-doctorate research fellow and data scientist at Mayo Clinic Artificial Intelligence Laboratory and the Orthopedic Surgery Artificial Intelligence Laboratory (OSAIL), Mayo Clinic. His daily job includes programming, data science research, and looking to apply artificial intelligence in medicine and medical imaging.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
