<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications on OSAIL</title>
    <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Publications on OSAIL</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>All You Need is 20 Images: Few-shot Image Segmentation Using Denoising Diffusion Probabilistic Models</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_cmimi_ddpm/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_cmimi_ddpm/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Applying Deep Learning to Establish a Total Hip Arthroplasty Radiography Registry: A Stepwise Approach</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_cmimi_styleganimggen/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_cmimi_styleganimggen/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Applying Deep Learning to Establish a Total Hip Arthroplasty Radiography Registry: A Stepwise Approach</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_cmimi_tharegistry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_cmimi_tharegistry/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Applying Deep Learning to Establish a Total Hip Arthroplasty Radiography Registry: A Stepwise Approach</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_siim_tharegistry/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_siim_tharegistry/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting risk of dislocation after total hip arthroplasty from preoperative radiographs: A multitask multimodal deep learning approach</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_siim_thadiscalc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_siim_thadiscalc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Denoising Diffusion Probabilistic Models to Create High Resolution Synthetic Pelvis Radiographs</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_cmimi_supersizedimg/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_cmimi_supersizedimg/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Applying Deep Learning to Establish a Total Hip Arhroplasty Radiography Registry: A Stepwise Approach</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_jbjs_tharegistry/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_jbjs_tharegistry/</guid>
      <description>Background: Establishing imaging registries for large patient cohorts is challenging because manual labeling is tedious and relying solely on DICOM (digital imaging and communications in medicine) metadata can result in errors. We endeavored to establish an automated hip and pelvic radiography registry of total hip arthroplasty (THA) patients by utilizing deep-learning pipelines. The aims of the study were (1) to utilize these automated pipelines to identify all pelvic and hip radiographs with appropriate annotation of laterality and presence or absence of implants, and (2) to automatically measure acetabular component inclination and version for THA images.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multicenter Validation of Natural Language Processing Algorithms for the Detection of Common Data Elements in Operative Notes for Total Hip Arthroplasty: Algorithm Development and Validation</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_jmir_nlp_validationthaopnote/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_jmir_nlp_validationthaopnote/</guid>
      <description>Background: Natural language processing (NLP) methods are powerful tools for extracting and analyzing critical information from free-text data. MedTaggerIE, an open-source NLP pipeline for information extraction based on text patterns, has been widely used in the annotation of clinical notes. A rule-based system, MedTagger-total hip arthroplasty (THA), developed based on MedTaggerIE, was previously shown to correctly identify the surgical approach, fixation, and bearing surface from the THA operative notes at Mayo Clinic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distribution and Correlates of Hip-Knee-Ankle Angle in Early Osteoarthritis and Preoperative Total Knee Arthroplasty Patients</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_joa_mip_hipkneeankleangle/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_joa_mip_hipkneeankleangle/</guid>
      <description>Background: Several studies have investigated the distribution of hip-knee-ankle (HKA) angle in healthy populations; however, few have evaluated this metric in patients undergoing total knee arthroplasty (TKA). The purpose of this study is to compare HKA angle distribution in early and advanced knee osteoarthritis (OA) patients.
Methods: Full limb radiographs were used to measure HKA angle for 983 subjects from the Osteoarthritis Initiative (OAI) cohort and 4,901 pre-TKA patients from an institutional cohort.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Identifying Modifiable and Nonmodifiable Cost Drivers of Ambulatory Rotator Cuff Repair: A Machine Learning Analysis</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_jses_ml_costrcr/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_jses_ml_costrcr/</guid>
      <description>Introduction: Implementing novel tools that identify contributors to the cost of orthopedic procedures can help hospitals maximize efficiency, minimize waste, improve surgical decision-making, and practice value-based care. The purpose of this study was to develop and internally validate a machine learning algorithm to identify key drivers of total charges after ambulatory arthroscopic rotator cuff repair and compare its performance with a state-of-the-art statistical learning model.
Methods: A retrospective review of the New York State Ambulatory Surgery and Services Database was performed to identify patients who underwent elective outpatient rotator cuff repair (RCR) from 2015 to 2016.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning for Radiographic Measurement of Femoral Componenent Subsidence Following Total Hip Arthroplasty</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_radai_mip_thasubsidence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_radai_mip_thasubsidence/</guid>
      <description>Femoral component subsidence following total hip arthroplasty (THA) is a worrisome radiographic finding. This study developed and evaluated a deep learning tool to automatically quantify femoral component subsidence between two serial anteroposterior (AP) hip radiographs. The authors&amp;rsquo; institutional arthroplasty registry was used to retrospectively identify patients who underwent primary THA from 2000 to 2020. A deep learning dynamic U-Net model was trained to automatically segment femur, implant, and magnification markers on a dataset of 500 randomly selected AP hip radiographs from 386 patients with polished tapered cemented femoral stems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Redefining the 3D Topography of the Acetabular Safe Zone: A Multivariable Study Evaluating Prosthetic Hip Stability</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_aaos_acetabularsafezone/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_aaos_acetabularsafezone/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creation of a Total Hip Arthroplasty Patient Specific Dislocation Risk Calculator Augmented by Deep Learning Radiograph Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_aaos_thadislocation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_aaos_thadislocation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning Tool for Accurate and Precise Automatic Measurement of Femoral Component Subsidence Following Total Hip Arthroplasty from Plan Radiographs</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_aaos_thasubsidence/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_aaos_thasubsidence/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Redefining the 3D Topography of the Acetabular Safe Zone: A Multivariable Study Evaluating Prosthetic Hip Stability</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_jbjs_mip_acetabularsafezone/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/22_jbjs_mip_acetabularsafezone/</guid>
      <description>Background: Dislocation is the most common reason for early revision following total hip arthroplasty (THA). More than 40 years ago, Lewinnek et al. proposed an acetabular &amp;ldquo;safe zone&amp;rdquo; to avoid dislocation. While novel at the time, their study was substantially limited according to modern standards. The purpose of this study was to determine optimal acetabular cup positioning during THA as well as the effect of surgical approach on the topography of the acetabular safe zone and the hazard of dislocation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning Tool for Accurate and Precise Automatic Measurement of Femoral Component Subsidence Following THA</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_aahks_thasubsidence/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_aahks_thasubsidence/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning Artificial Intelligence Model for Prediction of Hip Dislocation Following Primary Total Hip Arthroplasty From Anteroposterior Radiographs</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_aaos_thadisrisk/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_aaos_thadisrisk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Deep Learning Tool for Automated Radiographic Measurement of Acetabular Component Inclination and Version After Total Hip Arthroplasty</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_joa_mip_thaacetabularangles/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_joa_mip_thaacetabularangles/</guid>
      <description>Background: Inappropriate acetabular component angular position is believed to increase the risk of hip dislocation after total hip arthroplasty. However, manual measurement of these angles is time consuming and prone to interobserver variability. The purpose of this study was to develop a deep learning tool to automate the measurement of acetabular component angles on postoperative radiographs.
Methods: Two cohorts of 600 anteroposterior (AP) pelvis and 600 cross-table lateral hip postoperative radiographs were used to develop deep learning models to segment the acetabular component and the ischial tuberosities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning Artificial Intelligence Model for Assessment of Hip Dislocation Risk Following Primary Total hip Arthroplasty from Postoperative Radiographs</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_joa_riskpred_thadislocation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_joa_riskpred_thadislocation/</guid>
      <description>Background: Dislocation is a common complication following total hip arthroplasty (THA), and accounts for a high percentage of subsequent revisions. The purpose of this study is to illustrate the potential of a convolutional neural network model to assess the risk of hip dislocation based on postoperative anteroposterior pelvis radiographs.
Methods: We retrospectively evaluated radiographs for a cohort of 13,970 primary THAs with 374 dislocations over 5 years of follow-up. Overall, 1490 radiographs from dislocated and 91,094 from non-dislocated THAs were included in the analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning Tool for Accurate and Precise Automatic Measurement of Femoral Component Subsidence Following Total Hip Arthroplasty from Plan Radiographs</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_mayoai_thasubsidence/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_mayoai_thasubsidence/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use of Natural Language Processing Algorithms to Identify Common Data Elements in Operative Notes for Knee Arthroplasty</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_joa_nlp_tkaopnote/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_joa_nlp_tkaopnote/</guid>
      <description>Background: Natural language processing (NLP) methods have the capability to process clinical free text in electronic health records, decreasing the need for costly manual chart review, and improving data quality. We developed rule-based NLP algorithms to automatically extract surgery specific data elements from knee arthroplasty operative notes.
Methods: Within a cohort of 20,000 knee arthroplasty operative notes from 2000 to 2017 at a large tertiary institution, we randomly selected independent pairs of training and test sets to develop and evaluate NLP algorithms to detect five major data elements.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Autommated Detection of Periprosthetic Joint Infections and Data Elements Using Natural Language Processing</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_joa_nlp_pji/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/21_joa_nlp_pji/</guid>
      <description>Background: Periprosthetic joint infection (PJI) data elements are contained in both structured and unstructured documents in electronic health records and require manual data collection. The goal of this study is to develop a natural language processing (NLP) algorithm to replicate manual chart review for PJI data elements.
Methods: PJI was identified among all total joint arthroplasty (TJA) procedures performed at a single academic institution between 2000 and 2017. Data elements that comprise the Musculoskeletal Infection Society (MSIS) criteria were manually extracted and used as the gold standard for validation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning Artificial Intelligence Model for Assessment of Hip Dislocation Risk Following Primary Total Hip Arthroplasty From Postoperative Radiographs</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/20_rsna_thadisrisk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/20_rsna_thadisrisk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning Artificial Intelligence Model for Measurement of the Acetabular Inclination and Anteversion Angles Following Total Hip Arthroplasty</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/20_cmimi_thaacetabularangles/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/20_cmimi_thaacetabularangles/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning Artificial Intelligence Model for Prediction of Hip Dislocation Following Primary Total Hip Arthroplasty From Postoperative Radiographs</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/20_cmimi_thadisrisk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/20_cmimi_thadisrisk/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use of Natural Language Processing Algorithms to Identify Common Data Elements in Operative Notes for Total Hip Arthroplasty</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/19_jbjs_nlp_thaopnote/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/19_jbjs_nlp_thaopnote/</guid>
      <description>Background: Manual chart review is labor-intensive and requires specialized knowledge possessed by highly trained medical professionals. Natural language processing (NLP) tools are distinctive in their ability to extract critical information from raw text in electronic health records (EHRs). As a proof of concept for the potential application of this technology, we examined the ability of NLP to correctly identify common elements described by surgeons in operative notes for total hip arthroplasty (THA).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use of Natural Language Processing Tools to Identify and Classify Periprosthetic Femur Fractures</title>
      <link>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/19_joa_nlp_ppfx/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://orthopedicsurgeryailab.github.io/publications/19_joa_nlp_ppfx/</guid>
      <description>Background: Manual chart review is labor-intensive and requires specialized knowledge possessed by highly trained medical professionals. The cost and infrastructure challenges required to implement this is prohibitive for most hospitals. Natural language processing (NLP) tools are distinctive in their ability to extract critical information from unstructured text in the electronic health records. As a simple proof-of-concept for the potential application of NLP technology in total hip arthroplasty (THA), we examined its ability to identify periprosthetic femur fractures (PPFFx) followed by more complex Vancouver classification.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
